When I was invited to give this talk a couple of months ago,
عندما دُعيت لإلقاء هذة المحادثة قبل بضعة شهور،
we discussed a number of titles with the organizers,
ناقشنا عدداً من العناوين مع المُنظمين،
and a lot of different items were kicked around and were discussed.
و تم طرح و مناقشة العديد من البنود المختلفة .
But nobody suggested this one,
و لكن أحدًا لم يقترح (هزيمة لإيبولا).
and the reason for that was two months ago,
والسبب في ذلك كان قبل شهرين،
Ebola was escalating exponentially
عندما كان مرض الإيبولا يتصاعد سريعاً
and spreading over wider geographic areas than we had ever seen,
وكان قد انتشر في مناطق جغرافية أكبر و أكثر من أي وقت مضى.
and the world was terrified, concerned and alarmed
حيث كان العالم خائفاً، و قلقاً و حذراً
by this disease, in a way we've not seen in recent history.
من هذا المرض، بطريقة لم نرها في تاريخنا المعاصر.
But today, I can stand here and I can talk to you about beating Ebola
ولكن اليوم، يمكنني أن أقف هنا وأتحدث إليكم عن هزيمة الإيبولا
because of people whom you've never heard of,
بسبب أُناس لم تسمعوا عنهم أبداً.
people like Peter Clement, a Liberian doctor who's working in Lofa County,
أشخاص مثل بيتر كليمنت، و هو طبيب ليبيري يعمل في مقاطعة (لوفا)،
a place that many of you have never heard of, probably, in Liberia.
و هي مكان في ليبيريا لم يسمع العديد منكم عنه، على الأغلب.
The reason that Lofa County is so important
والسبب في أهمية مقاطعة (لوفا)
is because about five months ago,
هو أنه قبل نحو خمسة أشهر،
when the epidemic was just starting to escalate,
عند بداية تصاعد الوباء،
Lofa County was right at the center, the epicenter of this epidemic.
كانت مقاطعة لوفا في المركز، و بؤرة هذا الوباء.
At that time, MSF and the treatment center there,
في ذلك الوقت، كانت منظمة (أطباء بلا حدود) ومركز العلاج هناك،
they were seeing dozens of patients every single day,
يعاينون أعداداً كبيرة من المرضى يومياً،
and these patients, these communities were becoming more and more terrified
حيث كان هؤلاء المرضى، و هذه المجتمعات يصبحون أكثر ذعراً
as time went by, with this disease and what it was doing to their families,
مع مرور الوقت، مع هذا المرض وتأثيرهُ على أُسرِهم،
to their communities, to their children, to their relatives.
على مجتمعاتهم، على أطفالهم، و أقاربهم.
And so Peter Clement was charged with driving that 12-hour-long rough road
ولهذا كان بيتر كليمنت يقود 12 ساعة في طريق وعِر
from Monrovia, the capital, up to Lofa County,
من العاصمة مونروفيا، إلى مقاطعة لوفا،
to try and help bring control to the escalating epidemic there.
في محاولة للسيطرة على الوباء المتصاعد هناك.
And what Peter found when he arrived was the terror that I just mentioned to you.
وعند وصولهِ، وجد بيتر ذلك الرعب الذي ذكرته للتو.
So he sat down with the local chiefs, and he listened.
ولذلك قام بالإجتماع مع المسؤولين المحليين، و استمع إليهم.
And what he heard was heartbreaking.
وما سمعه كان مُفجعاً.
He heard about the devastation and the desperation
سمع عن دمار و يأس
of people affected by this disease.
الأشخاص المتضررين من هذا المرض.
He heard the heartbreaking stories
استمع لقصص تفطر الفؤاد
about not just the damage that Ebola did to people,
ليس فقط عن الضرر الذي أحدثه الإيبولا بالمرضى,
but what it did to families and what it did to communities.
و لكن عما لحق بعوائل، و مجتمعات أيضاً.
And he listened to the local chiefs there and what they told him --
فاستمع للمسؤولين المحليين هناك و ما قالوه له.
They said, "When our children are sick, when our children are dying,
قالوا, "عندما يمرض أطفالنا، عندما يحتضر أطفالنا،
we can't hold them at a time when we want to be closest to them.
فإننا لا نستطيع أن نُعانقهم في وقت نحتاج ان نكون فيه الأقرب أليهم
When our relatives die, we can't take care of them as our tradition demands.
وعندما يموت أقاربنا، فإننا لا نستطيع أن نرعاهم كما تتطلب تقاليدنا.
We are not allowed to wash the bodies to bury them
لا يُسمح لنا بغسلِ جثثهِم لدفنها
the way our communities and our rituals demand.
كما هو مُتطلب في قيمنا و مجتمعاتنا.
And for this reason, they were deeply disturbed, deeply alarmed
ولهذا السبب، كانوا قلقين و منزعجين جداً
and the entire epidemic was unraveling in front of them.
فالوباء قد انكشف أمامهم كاملاً.
People were turning on the healthcare workers who had come,
بدأ الناس باللجوء إلى العاملين بمراكز الرعاية الصحية،
the heroes who had come to try and help save the community,
هؤلاء الأبطال الذين قدِموا ليحاولوا و ينقذوا المجتمع،
to help work with the community, and they were unable to access them.
للمساعدة في العمل مع المجتمع، والتي لم يكن الوصول إليه سهلاً.
And what happened then was Peter explained to the leaders.
بعد ذلك، شرحَ بيتر الكثير للقادة هناك.
The leaders listened. They turned the tables.
استمع القادة و تحاوطوا على الطاولة.
And Peter explained what Ebola was. He explained what the disease was.
و أوضح بيتر ماهو مرض الإيبولا. شرح ماهية المرض.
He explained what it did to their communities.
وأوضح تأثيره على مجتمعاتهم.
And he explained that Ebola threatened everything that made us human.
و أوضح لهم أن الإيبولا يهدد الإنسانية بأجمعها.
Ebola means you can't hold your children the way you would in this situation.
الإيبولا يعني أنك لا تستطيع معانقة أولادك كما يجب في مثل هكذا وضع.
You can't bury your dead the way that you would.
يمنعك من دفن موتاك بالطريقة التي تجب.
You have to trust these people in these space suits to do that for you.
يجب أن تثق في أولئك الغرباء ذوو البدل الفضائية لدفنهم.
And ladies and gentlemen, what happened then was rather extraordinary:
فسيداتي وسادتي، ما حدث بعد ذلك كان اسثنائياً:
The community and the health workers, Peter, they sat down together
اجتمع العاملون في مجال الصحة، و بيتر، و المجتمع هناك
and they put together a new plan for controlling Ebola in Lofa County.
ورسموا خطة جديدة للسيطرة على الإيبولا في مقاطعة لوفا
And the reason that this is such an important story, ladies and gentlemen,
و السبب في أهمية هذه القصة، سيداتي وسادتي
is because today, this county, which is right at the center of this epidemic
هو أنه اليوم، في هذه المقاطعة و التي تقع في مركز هذا الوباء
you've been watching, you've been seeing in the newspapers,
الذي كنت تراقبونه، و ترونه في الصُحف،
you've been seeing on the television screens,
و تروه على شاشات التلفاز،
today Lofa County is nearly eight weeks without seeing a single case of Ebola.
اليوم، مضى ما يُقارب الثمانية أسابيع دون ظهور إشارة واحدة من وباء الايبولا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, this doesn't mean that the job is done, obviously.
اللآن، هذا لا يعني أن المهمة قد أُنجزت, بالطبع.
There's still a huge risk that there will be additional cases there.
لا يزال هناك خطر كبير لظهور حالات إضافية هناك.
But what it does teach us is that Ebola can be beaten.
لكن ما نتعلمه، هو أنه بإمكاننا هزيمة الايبولا.
That's the key thing.
هذا هو الشيء الرئيسي.
Even on this scale,
حتى على هذا المستوى،
even with the rapid kind of growth that we saw in this environment here,
حتى مع هذا النمو السريع الذي رأيناه في تلك البيئة،
we now know Ebola can be beaten.
فإننا نعلم جيداً، أنه بإمكاننا هزيمة الإيبولا.
When communities come together with health care workers, work together,
عندما يتكاتف المجمتع و العاملين في مجال الرعاية الصحية، و يعملوا سوياً
that's when this disease can be stopped.
عندها يمكننا إيقاف هذا المرض.
But how did Ebola end up in Lofa County in the first place?
و لكن في المقام الأول، كيف وصلت الإيبولا إلى مقاطعة لوفا؟
Well, for that, we have to go back 12 months, to the start of this epidemic.
حسناً، لمعرفة ذلك ،علينا أن نعود 12 شهرًا، إلى بداية هذا الوباء.
And as many of you know, this virus went undetected,
ولعل العديد منكم يعلم، بدأ الفيروس بالإنتشار دون أن يُكشف
it evaded detection for three or four months when it began.
لم يُكشف عنه لمدة 3 أو 4 أشهر عندما بدأ
That's because this is not a disease of West Africa,
هذا و لأنه لم يكن معروفاً في غرب أفريقيا.
it's a disease of Central Africa, half a continent away.
هو مرض يُعرف في وسط أفريقيا. أي على نصف قارّة.
People hadn't seen the disease before;
لم يرى الناس هذا المرض من قبل.
health workers hadn't seen the disease before.
لم يرى عاملو الصحة هذا المرض من قبل.
They didn't know what they were dealing with,
لم يعلموا كيفية التعامل مع الأمر،
and to make it even more complicated,
و ما جعل الأمر أكثر تعقيداً،
the virus itself was causing a symptom, a type of a presentation
كان الفيروس يسبب أعراضاً، ظهوراً نوعياً
that wasn't classical of the disease.
لم تكن من المُتعارف عليه لهذا المرض.
So people didn't even recognize the disease, people who knew Ebola.
لذلك، لم يستطع حتى الأشخاص، الذين يُميزون الإيبولا التعرُف عليه
For that reason it evaded detection for some time,
لذلك، تفادى الإيبولا أن يُكشف عنه لفترة من الزمن
But contrary to public belief sometimes these days,
ولكن خلافاً للإعتقاد السائد أحياناً في هذه الأيام،
once the virus was detected, there was a rapid surge in of support.
عندما تم الكشف عن الفيروس، كان هناك موجة سريعة من الدعم.
MSF rapidly set up an Ebola treatment center, as many of you know, in the area.
سارعت منظمة أطباء بلا حدود بإنشاء مركز لعلاجه,كما يعلم الكثير في المنطقة .
The World Health Organization and the partners that it works with
منظمة الصحة العالمية و شركائها التى تعمل معهم
deployed eventually hundreds of people over the next two months
أعلنت مؤخرًا عن مئات الأشخاص علي مدار الشهرين القادمين
to be able to help track the virus.
قادرين علي تتبع الفيروس.
The problem, ladies and gentlemen, is by then, this virus,
المشكلة , أيها السيدات و السادة أنه بحلول هذا الوقت , هذا الفيروس,
well known now as Ebola, had spread too far.
الذي يعرف الآن بالإيبولا, كان قد انتشر بشكل كبير.
It had already outstripped what was one of the largest responses
فهو بالفعل فاق عما كان واحدًا من أكبر ردود الفعل
that had been mounted so far to an Ebola outbreak.
التى شُنت حتى الآن لتفشي مرض الإيبولا.
By the middle of the year, not just Guinea
بحلول منتصف العام , ليس فقط غينيا
but now Sierra Leone and Liberia were also infected.
و لكن الآن سيراليون و ليبيريا أُصيبوا بالعدوى أيضًا .
As the virus was spreading geographically, the numbers were increasing
في أثناء انتشار الفيروس جغرافياَ, كان العدد في ازدياد
and at this time, not only were hundreds of people infected
و في ذلك الوقت, لم يكن فقط المئات من المصابين
and dying of the disease,
و المحتضرين من هذا المرض,
but as importantly, the front line responders,
و لكن الأهم , المستجيبين في الصفوف الأولى,
the people who had gone to try and help,
من ذهبوا للمحاولة و المساعدة ,
the health care workers, the other responders
العاملون في مجال الرعاية الصحية ، و مستجيبون آخرون
were also sick and dying by the dozens.
كانوا أيضًا مرضي و يحتضرون و يقدرون بالعشرات.
The presidents of these countries recognized the emergencies.
أدرك رؤساء تلك الدول الحالة الطارئة.
They met right around that time, they agreed on common action
و اجتمعوا معاً حينها و اتفقوا على مبادرة مشتركة
and they put together an emergency joint operation center in Conakry
و وضعوا مركز عمليات مشترك للطوارئ في كوناكري
to try and work together to finish this disease and get it stopped,
في محاولةٍ للعمل معاً على إيقاف هذا المرض و إنهائه,
to implement the strategies we talked about.
لينفذوا الاستراتيجيات التي تحدثنا عنها.
But what happened then was something we had never seen before with Ebola.
و لكن ما حدث لاحقاً كان شيئاً لم نعهده سابقاً مع الإيبولا.
What happened then was the virus, or someone sick with the virus,
ما حدث هو أن الفيروس, أو أن شخصأً مصاباً به,
boarded an airplane, flew to another country,
التحق بطائرة و سافر إلى بلدٍ آخر،
and for the first time, we saw in another distant country
و لأول مرة, رأينا في بلدٍ مختلف
the virus pop up again.
ظهور الفيروس من جديد.
This time it was in Nigeria, in the teeming metropolis of Lagos,
و هذه المرة في نيجيريا، في العاصمة المزدحمة لاغوس
21 million people.
21 مليون نسمة
Now the virus was in that environment.
الآن الفيروس في هذه البيئة
international concern on a scale that we hadn't seen in recent years
قلق دولي على نطاق لم نره من قبل
caused by a disease like this.
مُسبب من مرض كهذا.
The World Health Organization immediately called together an expert panel,
دعت منظمة الصحة العالمية فورياً لإطلاق لجنة خبراء،
looked at the situation, declared an international emergency.
نظرت في الوضع، و أعلنت حالة الطوارئ دوليًا.
And in doing so, the expectation would be that there would be a huge outpouring
و بذلك، كان من المتوقع أن يكون هناك موجة جارفة
of international assistance to help these countries
من المساعدة الدولية بمساعدة هذه البلدان
which were in so much trouble and concern at that time.
التي تعاني من الكثير من المتاعب و القلق في هذا الوقت.
But what we saw was something very different.
لكن ما رأيناه كان شيئًا مختلفًا.
There was some great response.
كان هناك استجابة واسعة.
A number of countries came to assist -- many, many NGOs and others, as you know,
العديد من البلدان أتت للمساعدة، العديد من المنظمات غير حكومية و غيرهم كما تعلمون
but at the same time, the opposite happened in many places.
لكن بنفس الوقت، حدث العكس في العديد من المناطق.
Alarm escalated, and very soon these countries found themselves
تصاعد التنبيه، و قريبًا وجدت هذه البلدان
not receiving the support they needed, but increasingly isolated.
عدم تلقيها الدعم المطلوب، بل معزولة بشكل متزايد.
What we saw was commercial airlines [stopped] flying into these countries
ما رأيناه كان أن شركات الطيران التجارية التي تحلق فوق هذه البلدان
and people who hadn't even been exposed to the virus
و حتى الناس الذين لم يتعرضوا للفيروس
were no longer allowed to travel.
لم يسمح لهم بالسفر.
This caused not only problems, obviously, for the countries themselves,
لم يسبب هذا المشاكل فحسب، بالطبع، إلى البلدان نفسها،
but also for the response.
بل إلى الإستجابة.
Those organizations that were trying to bring people in,
تلك المنظمات التي كانت تحاول أن تجمع الناس،
to try and help them respond to the outbreak,
في محاولة لمساعدتهم على عدم تفشي المرض،
they could not get people on airplanes,
لم تستطع أن تضع الناس في الطائرات،
they could not get them into the countries to be able to respond.
لم تستطع أن تعيدهم إلى البلدان لمعالجتهم.
In that situation, ladies and gentleman,
في هذه الحالة، سيداتي سادتي،
a virus like Ebola takes advantage.
فيروس كالإيبولا يأخذ الأفضلية في الإنتشار.
And what we saw then was something also we hadn't seen before.
وما رأيناه بعد ذلك كان شيئًا لم نره من قبل.
Not only did this virus continue in the places
لم يستمر الفيروس في المناطق
where they'd already become infected, but then it started to escalate
التي كانت مصابة به فحسب، بل بدأ يتصاعد
and we saw the case numbers that you see here,
و بدأنا برؤية الأرقام التي ترونها هنا،
something we'd never seen before on such a scale,
شيئًا لم نره كم قبل بمثل هكذا مستوى،
an exponential increase of Ebola cases
زيادة هائلة في حالات الإيبولا
not just in these countries or the areas already infected in these countries
ليس بهذه البلدان أو المناطق التي كانت مصابة مسبقًا فحسب
but also spreading further and deeper into these countries.
بل انتشر في مناطق أبعد منها.
Ladies and gentleman, this was one of the most concerning
سيداتي و سادتي، كانت هذه من أكثر الحالات
international emergencies in public health we've ever seen.
المقلقة و الطارئة في الصحة العامة كنا قد شاهدناها أبدا.
And what happened in these countries then,
و ما حدث بعدها في هذه البلدان،
many of you saw, again, on the television, read about in the newspapers,
العديد منكم شاهدوا، مرةً أخرى، على التلفاز أو قرؤا عنه في الجرائد،
we saw the health system start to collapse under the weight of this epidemic.
شاهدنا النظام الصحي يبدأ في الإنهيار تحت وطأة هذا الوباء.
We saw the schools begin to close, markets no longer started,
شاهدنا المدارس تُغلق، أسواق لم تبدأ مجددًا،
no longer functioned the way that they should in these countries.
لم تعد إلى العمل بالطريقة التي كانت تعمل بها قبلاً في هذه البلدان.
We saw that misinformation and misperceptions started to spread
رأينا التضليل و التصورات الخاطئة قد بدأت بالإنتشار
even faster through the communities, which became even more alarmed
حتى بشكل أسرع خلال هذه المجتمعات، التي أصبحت أكثر حذرا
about the situation.
إزاء الوضع.
They started to recoil from those people that you saw in those space suits,
بدأوا بالنفور من أصحاب البذات الفضائية الذين يرونهم،
as they call them, who had come to help them.
كما أطقوا عليهم، الذين أتوا لمساعدتهم.
And then the situation deteriorated even further.
ثم تدهور الوضع أكثر من ذلك.
The countries had to declare a state of emergency.
كان على البلدان إعلان حالة الطوارئ
Large populations needed to be quarantined in some areas, and then riots broke out.
أعداد هائلة من البشر كان يجب عزلها في بعض المناطق، و اندلعت أعمال الشغب.
It was a very, very terrifying situation.
كان الوضع مرعبًا جدًا جدًا.
Around the world, many people began to ask,
بدأ يتسائل العديد من الناس حول العالم
can we ever stop Ebola when it starts to spread like this?
هل يمكننا إيقاف إنتشار الإيبولا بتوسعه هذا؟
And they started to ask, how well do we really know this virus?
و بدأوا بالتساؤل، كيف سنتعرف على هذا الفيروس جيدًا؟
The reality is we don't know Ebola extremely well.
في الحقيقة نحن لا نعرف الإيبولا إلى حد كبير.
It's a relatively modern disease in terms of what we know about it.
إنه مرض حديث نسبيا عما نعرفه عنه.
We've known the disease only for 40 years,
لقد تعرفنا عليه منذ 40 سنة فقط
since it first popped up in Central Africa in 1976.
عندما برزللمرة الأولى في وسط أفريقيا في عام 1976
But despite that, we do know many things:
و بغض النظر عن هذا، فنحن نعلم العديد من الأشياء:
We know that this virus probably survives in a type of a bat.
نعلم أن هذا الفيروس يعيش في نوع معين من الخفاش
We know that it probably enters a human population
نعلم أنه من المرجح دخل إلى التجمعات الشعبية
when we come in contact with a wild animal
عندما قمنا بالاتصال مع الحيوانات المتوحشة
that has been infected with the virus and probably sickened by it.
التي كانت مصابة بالفيروس مسبقًا و أمرضت البشر به.
Then we know that the virus spreads from person to person
و نعلم أن الفيروس انتشر من شخص لشخص
through contaminated body fluids.
من السوائل البشرية المسممة
And as you've all seen,
و كما شاهدتم جميعكم،
we know the horrific disease that it then causes in humans,
نعلم ما يسببه هذا المرض المرعب في البشر،
where we see this disease cause severe fevers, diarrhea, vomiting,
حيث شاهدناه يسبب حمة، إسهال، غثيان، إقياء
and then unfortunately, in 70 percent of the cases or often more, death.
و في 70% من الحالات أو أكثر أحيانًا يسبب الموت للأسف
This is a very dangerous, debilitating, and deadly disease.
إنه خطير جدًا، موهن ، و مرض مميت.
But despite the fact that we've not known this disease for a particularly long time,
و بغض النظر عن حقيقة أننا لم نعرف هذا المرض لمدة طويلة،
and we don't know everything about it, we do know how to stop this disease.
و لا نعرف كل شيء عنه، نعلم كيف نوقف هذا المرض.
There are four things that are critical to stopping Ebola.
هناك أربعة أمور حساسة لإيقاف الإيبولا.
First and foremost, the communities have got to understand this disease,
الأول و اﻷهم، على المجتمعات أن تفهم هذا المرض،
they've got to understand how it spreads and how to stop it.
عليهم تفهم كيفية انتشاره و كيفية إيقافه.
And then we've got to be able to have systems that can find every single case,
و من ثم علينا إيجاد منظومة لإيجاد جميع المصابين واحدًا واحدًا،
every contact of those cases,
جميع المتصلين بهذه الحالات،
and begin to track the transmission chains so that you can stop transmission.
و البدء بتتبع حركة هذه السلاسل لإيقاف الإنتقال.
We have to have treatment centers, specialized Ebola treatment centers,
علينا بإنشاء مراكز معالجة متخصصة، مراكز معالجة الإيبولا،
where the workers can be protected
حيث يتم حماية العاملين
as they try to provide support to the people who are infected,
كما يعملون هم على تزويد الأشخاص المصابين بالدعم
so that they might survive the disease.
لإنقاذهم من هذا المرض.
And then for those who do die,
و الذين قد ماتوا،
we have to ensure there is a safe, but at the same time dignified, burial process,
علينا التأكد من دفنهم بطريقة آمنة، و لائقة بنفس الوقت لضمان
so that there is no spread at that time as well.
عدم الإنتشار
So we do know how to stop Ebola, and these strategies work, ladies and gentlemen.
إذاً, نعلم كيف نوقف الإيبولا، و قد نجحت هذه الإستراتيجيات، سيداتي سادتي
The virus was stopped in Nigeria by these four strategies
تم إيقاف الفيروس في نيجيريا عن طريق هذه الإستراتيجيات الأربعة.
and the people implementing them, obviously.
و بدأ الناس بتطبيقها، بالطبع.
It was stopped in Senegal, where it had spread, and also in the other countries
تم إيقافه في السنغال حيث انتشر، و أيضاً في بلدان أخرى
that were affected by this virus, in this outbreak.
تعرضت، و انتشر فيها الفيروس.
So there's no question that these strategies actually work.
لذلك فليس هناك شك أن هذه الإستراتيجيات فعلًا نجحت.
The big question, ladies and gentlemen, was whether these strategies could work
السؤال الأكبر سيداتي سادتي، إما أن تعمل هذه الإستراتيجيات
on this scale, in this situation, with so many countries affected
على هذا الصعيد، في هذا الوضع مع العديد من البلدان المتأثرة
with the kind of exponential growth that you saw.
مع هذا النمو الأسي الذي رأيتموه.
That was the big question that we were facing just two or three months ago.
هذا كان السؤال الأكبر الذي واجهناه منذ شهرين أو ثلاثة.
Today we know the answer to that question.
اليوم نعلم جواب هذا السؤال.
And we know that answer because of the extraordinary work
و نعلم هذا الجواب بسبب العمل الإستثنائي
of an incredible group of NGOs, of governments, of local leaders,
لمجموعة من المنظمات الغير حكومية الرائعين، للحكومات، للقادة المحليين،
of U.N. agencies and many humanitarian and other organizations
لوكالات الأمم المتحدة و العديد من الإنسانيين و المنظمات الأخرى
that came and joined the fight to try and stop Ebola in West Africa.
الذين أتوا و انضموا إلى القتال ليحاولوا إيقاف الإيبولا في شرق أفريقيا.
But what had to be done there was slightly different.
و لكن ما وجب فعله كان مختلفًا قليلًا.
These countries took those strategies I just showed you;
أخذت هذه البلدان هذه الإستراتيجيات التي أريتكم إياها,
the community engagement, the case finding, contact tracing, etc.,
إشراك المجتمع، إكتشاف الحالات، تقصي المخالطين، الخ.،
and they turned them on their head.
ثم انقلبوا على رؤوسهم.
There was so much disease, they approached it differently.
كان هناك الكثير من الأمراض، التي اقتربوا منها بشكل مختلف.
What they decided to do was they would first try and slow down this epidemic
ما قرروا فعله هو أولًا محاولة إبطاء هذا الوياء
by rapidly building as many beds as possible in specialized treatment centers
بتركيب أكبر عدد ممكن من الأسرّة في مراكز المعالجة المتخصصة
so that they could prevent the disease from spreading from those were infected.
بحيث يمنعون المرض من الإنتشار من المصابين.
They would rapidly build out many, many burial teams
سيشكلون بسرعة العديد، و العديد من فرق الدفن
so that they could safely deal with the dead,
ليتعاملوا بشكل آمن مع المتوفين،
and with that, they would try and slow this outbreak
و بهذا، سيحاولون إبطاء هذا التفشي
to see if it could actually then be controlled using the classic approach
لمعرفة إذا كان بالإمكان السيطرة عليه باستخدام النهج التقليدي
of case finding and contact tracing.
في حالات إيجاد المصابين و اقتفاء المتصلين بهم.
And when I went to West Africa about three months ago,
و عندما ذهبت إلى شرق أفريقيا منذ حوالي ثلاثة أشهر،
when I was there what I saw was extraordinary.
عندما كنت هناك ما رأيته كان غير عادي.
I saw presidents opening emergency operation centers themselves against Ebola
رأيت رؤساء دول يفتتحون مراكز عمليات طارئة بأنفسهم ضد الإيبولا
so that they could personally coordinate and oversee and champion
بحيث ينسقون و يشرفون شخصيًا ويقودوا
this surge of international support to try and stop this disease.
هذا العدد الكبير من الدعم الدولي في محاولة لوقف هذا المرض.
We saw militaries from within those countries and from far beyond
شاهدنا العساكر من هذه البلدان و أخرى أبعد منها
coming in to help build Ebola treatment centers
آتين ليساعدوا في بناء مراكز معالجة الإيبولا
that could be used to isolate those who were sick.
التي ستستخدم لعزل أولئك الذين كانوا مرضى.
We saw the Red Cross movement working with its partner agencies on the ground there
شاهدنا حركة الصليب الأحمريعملون مع شركائهم من الوكالات على الأرض هناك
to help train the communities so that they could actually safely bury their dead
ليساعدوا في تدريب المجتمعات على دفن موتاهم بشكل آمن
in a dignified manner themselves.
و بشكل لائق بنفسهم.
And we saw the U.N. agencies, the World Food Program,
و شاهدنا وكالات الأمم المتحدة، منظمة برنامج الغذاء العالمي،
build a tremendous air bridge
يقومون ببناء جسر جوي هائل
that could get responders to every single corner of these countries rapidly
ليأتوا بالمستجيبين من كل زاوية من هذه البلدان بسرعة
to be able to implement the strategies that we just talked about.
ليكونوا قادرين على تنفيذ الإستراتيجيات التي تحدثنا عنها للتو.
What we saw, ladies and gentlemen, which was probably most impressive,
ما شاهدناه، سيداتي سادتي، من أكثر الأمور روعة،
was this incredible work by the governments,
العمل الرائع بين هذه الحكومات،
by the leaders in these countries, with the communities,
بين قادة هذه البلدان، مع المجتمعات،
to try to ensure people understood this disease,
لمحاولة التأكد أن االناس فهموا المرض،
understood the extraordinary things they would have to do to try and stop Ebola.
لفهم الأشياء الغيرعادية التي عليهم فعلها لإيقاف الإيبولا.
And as a result, ladies and gentlemen,
و نتيجةً لذلك، سيداتي سادتي،
we saw something that we did not know only two or three months earlier,
رأينا شيئًا لم نكن نعرفه في الشهرين أو الثلاثة السابقين،
whether or not it would be possible.
ما إذا كان من الممكن.
What we saw was what you see now in this graph,
ما رأيناه كان ما تراه في هذا المقطع،
when we took stock on December 1.
عندما أخذنا المؤشر في 1 ديسمبر.
What we saw was we could bend that curve, so to speak,
ما رأيناه أنه كان باستطاعتنا أن نحني هذا المنحنى، إذا جاز التعبير،
change this exponential growth,
تغيير هذا النمو المتسارع،
and bring some hope back to the ability to control this outbreak.
و إعادة بعض الأمل مجددًا إلى إمكانية السيطرة على هذا التفشي.
And for this reason, ladies and gentlemen, there's absolutely no question now
و لهذا السبب، سيداتي و سادتي، ليس هناك شك البتة
that we can catch up with this outbreak in West Africa and we can beat Ebola.
بأننا نستطيع اللحاق بهذا التفشي في شرق أفريقيا و أنه بإمكاننا هزيمة الإيبولا.
The big question, though, that many people are asking,
السؤال المهم، رغم ذلك، أن العديد من الناس يسألون
even when they saw this curve, they said,
حتى عندما شاهدوا هذا المنحنى، قالوا،
"Well, hang on a minute -- that's great you can slow it down,
"حسنًا, انتظر قليلًا -- إنه من العظيم أنه بإمكانك إبطائه،
but can you actually drive it down to zero?"
لكن هل يمكنك فعلًا أن تدفعه الى الصفر؟"
We already answered that question back at the beginning of this talk,
لقد أجبنا مسبقًا عن هذا السؤال في بداية هذه المحادثة،
when I spoke about Lofa County in Liberia.
عندما تكلمت عن مقاطعة لوفا في ليبيريا.
We told you the story how Lofa County got to a situation
أخبرناكم بقصة كيف أن مقاطعة لوفا وصلت إلى حالة
where they have not seen Ebola for eight weeks.
عدم ظهور الإيبولا إلى مدة ثمانية أسابيع.
But there are similar stories from the other countries as well.
و لكن هناك قصصًا مشابهة من البلدان الأخرى أيضًا.
From Gueckedou in Guinea,
من جوكيدو في غينيا،
the first area where the first case was actually diagnosed.
المنطقة الأولى التي شُخصت فيها أول حالة.
We've seen very, very few cases in the last couple of months,
لقد رأينا الكثير، الكثير من الحالات في آخر بضعة أشهر،
and here in Kenema, in Sierra Leone, another area in the epicenter,
و هنا في كينيما، في سيراليون، منطقة أخرى في مركز الزلازل،
we have not seen the virus for more than a couple of weeks --
لم نرى الفيروس لأكثر من بضعة أسابيع --
way too early to declare victory, obviously,
من المبكر جدًا إعلان النصر، طبعًا.،
but evidence, ladies and gentlemen,
لكن الدلائل، سيداتي سادتي،
not only can the response catch up to the disease,
ليس بإمكاننا الإستجابة و اللحاق بالمرض فحسب،
but this disease can be driven to zero.
بل يمكننا إيصاله إالى الصفر.
The challenge now, of course, is doing this on the scale needed
التحدي الآن، بالطبع، فعل ذلك على النطاق المحتاج إليه
right across these three countries, and that is a huge challenge.
عبر هذه البلدان الثلاثة، و هذا تحدي كبير.
Because when you've been at something for this long, on this scale,
لأنه عندما تكون في خضم شيئ لمدة طويلة و بهذا المستوى
two other big threats come in to join the virus.
فهناك خطران كبيران ينضمان الى خطر الفيروس.
The first of those is complacency,
الأول منهما هو التراخي،
the risk that as this disease curve starts to bend,
أن يتصاعد خطر هذا المرض،
the media look elsewhere, the world looks elsewhere.
وسائل الإعلام ستنظر في أماكن أخرى، العالم سينظر في مكان آخر.
Complacency always a risk.
التراخي دائمًا خطر.
And the other risk, of course, is when you've been working so hard for so long,
و الخطر الآخر، بالطبع، أنه عندما تكون تعمل بكل طاقتك و لمدة طويلة جدًا،
and slept so few hours over the past months,
و نمت بضع ساعات في الشهور الماضية،
people are tired, people become fatigued,
الناس تعبوا، الناس أصبحوا مُرهقين،
and these new risks start to creep into the response.
و هذه الأخطار الجديدة بدأت بالزحف على حساب الاستجابة.
Ladies and gentlemen, I can tell you today I've just come back from West Africa.
سيداتي سادتي، اليوم أستطيع أن أقول لكم بأنني قد عدت للتو من شرق أفريقيا.
The people of these countries, the leaders of these countries,
الناس في هذه البلدان، قادة هذه البلدان،
they are not complacent.
ليسوا بمتراخين.
They want to drive Ebola to zero in their countries.
يريدون أن ينهوا الإيبولا إلى المستوى صفر في بلادهم.
And these people, yes, they're tired, but they are not fatigued.
و هؤلاء الناس، نعم، لقد تعبوا، و لكنهم ليسوا بمرهقين.
They have an energy, they have a courage,
لديهم طاقة، لديهم الشجاعة،
they have the strength to get this finished.
لديهم القوة لإنهاء هذا.
What they need, ladies and gentlemen, at this point,
ما يحتاجونه، سيداتي سادتي، في هذه النقطة،
is the unwavering support of the international community,
هو الدعم الثابت من المجتمع الدولي،
to stand with them,
ليقف معهم،
to bolster and bring even more support at this time, to get the job finished.
لدعم وتقديم المزيد من الدعم في هذا الوقت، لإنهاء عملهم.
Because finishing Ebola right now means turning the tables on this virus,
لأن القضاء على الإيبولا الآن يعني قلب الطاولة على الفيروس،
and beginning to hunt it.
و بداية اصطياده.
Remember, this virus, this whole crisis, rather, started with one case,
اذكروا، الفيروس، هذه الأزمة، بدأت بحالة واحدة،
and is going to finish with one case.
و سينتهي بحالة واحدة.
But it will only finish if those countries have got enough epidemiologists,
و لكنه سينتهي عندما تحصل هذه البلدان على علماء أوبئة،
enough health workers, enough logisticians and enough other people working with them
عدد كاف من عاملي الصحة، و من اللوجستيين و عدد كاف من الناس ليعملوا معهم
to be able to find every one of those cases, track their contacts
ليكونوا قادرين على إيجاد أي حالة، و اقتفاء أثر المتصلين بها
and make sure that this disease stops once and for all.
و يتأكدوا أن هذا المرض قد توقف و إلى الأبد.
Ladies and gentleman, Ebola can be beaten.
سيداتي سادتي، يمكن هزيمة الإيبولا.
Now we need you to take this story out to tell it to the people who will listen
و الآن نريدكم أن تأخذوا هذه القصة إلى العلن و تخبروا من سيستمع من الناس
and educate them on what it means to beat Ebola,
و تعلموهم ما معنى أن تُهزم الإيبولا،
and more importantly, we need you to advocate with the people
و الأهم من هذا، نحتاجكم أن تدعوا الناس
who can help us bring the resources we need to these countries,
الذين باستطاعتهم مساعدتنا بجلب المصادر التي نحتاجها لهذه البلدان،
to beat this disease.
للقضاء على هذا المرض.
There are a lot of people out there who will survive and will thrive,
هناك العديد من الناس الذين سيتم إنقاذهم ليزدهروا،
in part because of what you do to help us beat Ebola.
و جزء من ذلك مساعدتكم لنا بالقضاء على الإيبولا.
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)